字幕制作：  cxj24394(TANK)  后期校對：  cxj24394(TANK)
■
公元4世紀晚期  羅馬帝國江河日下
The late fourth century A.D. the Roman Empire began to crumble.
地處于埃及行省的亞歷山大港
Alexandria, in the province of Egypt
如同落日余暉
still retained some of its luster,,
該港擁有古代世界七大奇跡之一
possessed one of the Seven Wonders of the ancient world:,
享譽盛名的亞歷山大燈塔
the legendary lighthouse
以及人類早期歷史上最偉大的圖書館
and the biggest library known.
這個書館不僅是文化寶庫  也是宗教象征
The library was a not only cultural but a religious symbol,,
多神教徒在此參拜他們的祖先神
a place where the pagans worshiped their ancestral gods.
如今傳統的多神教徒與猶太教徒
The traditional pagan worship in the city now coexisted,
在此共存
with the Jews,
同處于此還有屢禁不止的
and an unstoppable religion up to now banned,,
基督教
Christianity.
少有傻瓜會捫心自問
How many fools do you think have asked themselves?
星星為何不會從天空墜落
why don't the stars fall from the sky
可你不同  你受過智者的教育
But you, who've had the teachings of the wise,
你知道星星只會升起或落下
You know that the stars move neither up nor down.
自東至西轉動
they merely revolve from east to west,
沿著最完美的軌跡
following the most perfect course ever conceived,
做圓周運動
The circle.
風暴佳人
圓周運動主宰宇宙
Because the circle reigns in the heavens,
因而星星永不墜落
the stars have never fallen and they never will.
但是在地球上呢?
But, what about here on Earth?
在地球上  物體自由降落
Here, bodies do fall.
但是他們的運行軌跡  不是環形而是線形
But their movements are not circular but linear.
再看一次
Watch again.
別撿  放那兒
No, leave it.
那么
So,
你們認為在地面之下究竟蘊藏著
What mysterious wonder do you all think might be
何種神奇物質?
lurking beneath the Earth
使得人類  動物
that would make every single person and animal
所有的物體以及奴隸適得其所
and object and slaves circular?
那會是什么呢?
What might it be?
是重力  老師
The heaviness, lady.
不對
No.
辛奈西斯
Synesius.
因為他們的重量
The weightiness.
不對  你們說的是一樣東西
No, you're both speaking about the same thing,
但你們都沒有切中要害
but you're not talking about the primary course.
你們有沒有人想過你們的
Have any of you ever wondered that your,
你們的腳
that your feet,
your feet
站立在宇宙的正中央
are standing on the very center of the cosmos
而宇宙承載萬物
that holds all things together
并將萬物緊密相連
and pulls them together
如果沒有中心
If there were no center
那么宇宙將會混沌不清
then the universe would be
無窮無盡  無狀之狀  雜亂不堪
shapeless, infinite, formless, chaotic.
無論我們身處何方
Will it make a little difference,
都將毫無二致
if we were here or there or anywhere?
那我們不降臨人間豈不更好
And we'd all be better off never have been born.
公元391年  亞歷山大圖書館
Library of Alexandria 391 A.D.
神  我們之父
God, Our Father,
乃萬物之主
Lord of the universe,
萬物之源
origin of all things,
宇宙之永痧銃q
eternal force of the cosmos,
萬事萬物在此有始有終
where everything has its beginning and everything its end.
全能的塞拉皮斯
Almighty Serapis
伊希斯
Isis
荷魯斯
Horus
阿努比斯神
Anubis
以及所有凡間與天上
and all the other gods we ask for your protection.
給予子民保護的諸神
both in heaven and on earth,
市集上出事了
I don't know what's happening in the market.
我知道你對我也有感覺
I know you also feel something.
我看出了
I've seen.
請轉告主人我們要走了
Tell the master we're leaving.
難以置信
Can you believe?
他像我示愛還把我當成他的戰利品
He was courting me as if I'm one of his conquests.
真是有其父必有其子
This Orestes is as foolish as his father.
如果我建議他移情至另一位
I already suggested that he devote his heart to another muse
姿色更甚于我的女神
one more beautiful than I.
-誰?  -繆塞克
-Who? -Music.
音樂
Music?
他可沒像你笑得這么開心
He didn't find his music.
本來是227  怎會變成16呢?
What happen? 227 ever become 16.
看這個  這里是14
Look at this, it's 14.
他們的生活習性與人類無異
They behave like humans!
他們吃喝享樂  驕奢淫逸
They eat, drink and fornicate!
如果我的諸神也吃喝享樂  驕奢淫逸
If my gods  eat, drink and fornicate
豈不快哉
good for them.
不是這樣的  不是
Know this,Know this,
你們崇拜的形象沒有一絲神圣可言
you who console yourself with pagan images.
不管是男人女人  還是飛禽走獸
Men, women, birds, reptiles!
塞拉皮斯  塞拉皮斯
Serapis! Serapis!
誰會信仰把花盆當做皇冠的神呢?
Who could trust the God, need a flower pot for a crown?
你們這些基督徒啊
Hey you, Christians
羅馬帝國讓你們幸存于此
how arrogant you'd become now that the,
你們卻變得如此狂妄自大
Empire allows you to exist.
我的祖父曾看見他們
My father's father saw them
在競技場里被屠殺并用來喂獅子
slaughtered in the circus and fed to the lions.
打住  打住  看著
Enough! Enough! Watch.
看著
Watch.
我將穿越火坑
I shall now walk across the fire.
若我主是
If my God,
若我主是真神  我將會毫發無損
If my God is the true god, I shall suffer no harm.
然而如若你的主存在
If however, your gods exist
我就會像只豬一樣被烤死
they will roast me like a pig.
你
You,
你真勇敢
You're a lie!
你會被燒死的
你會遭到報應的
You'll get what you deserve.
現在我們來看看  你是否能穿越火坑?
Now, let's see if you can walk cross the fire.
你們想干嘛?
What are you doing?
住手  你們不能這樣  放開他
Stop, you can't do that! Let the man go.
閉嘴  多神教徒
Be quiet pagan
否則把你也拖進去
or we'd call you in as well.
這是誰的?
Whose is this?
我得重復多少遍?
How many times must I repeat myself?
今天  基督徒當眾燒傷了一名男子
Today, the Christians burned a man.
就在廣場中央
Right in the middle of the Agora!
我的屋子里嚴禁出現這種東西
I will not have this in my house!
賽昂家嚴禁此物
Not in the house of Theon!
給我
Give it to me.
Give it to me!
主人  望您開恩  對此既往不咎
Master, I beg mercy for your slave girl.
達烏斯  起來
Davus! Get up.
這與你無關
You have nothing to do with this.
我也是一名基督徒
I too, am a Christian.
你說什么?
What did you say?
我也是一名基督徒
I too, am a Christian.
連我也一并懲罰吧
Punish me for the both of us.
他們妄想教我們什么是仁慈
So, now they presume to teach us mercy.
-拿鞭子來  -父親
-Get a whip. -Father!
請您冷靜冷靜  好嗎?
Please wait until you calm before you,
父親  我求您了  我求您了
Father, I beg of you. I beg of you
他真的被燃燒的光亮包圍嗎?
wrapped in a blazing brightness.
傻子  那是真正的火焰
It was the flames, stupid.
那他為什么沒有像多神教徒那樣燃燒?
Then why didn't he burn like the pagan?
告訴我啊
Tell me.
請你回避一下
Leave us,
過來
Come here.
跪下吧
Kneel.
你真的是一名基督徒嗎?
Tell me, is it true that you're a Christian?
我不知該怎么說  女主人
I don't know what to say, Mistress.
什么意思?
Why not?
如果我說是  那就是欺騙您
If I said yes, that would be a lie.
如果我說不是  那就是欺騙主人
If I said no, that'd mean I lied to my master.
我不知哪個情節更嚴重?
I don't know which one's worst.
那你就該緘默不語
Then you should say nothing at all.
好了
There.
謝謝您
Thank you.
我想讓你知道主人對此很失望
I want you to know that the Master is upset with himself about this.
那是什么?
What is that?
是我做的小玩意  女主人
Something I made, Mistress.
這看上去像是一個
But it looks like a,
這到底是什么?
What is it?
這是托勒密的天體系統
It's Ptolemaic System.
的確如此
It is.
這是你做的嗎?
Did you do this?
這是地球
Earth
她是宇宙的中心
is the center of the cosmos
而環繞四周的有
and revolving around it
太陽以及5大行星
the Sun and the five wanderers:
水星  金星  火星  木星  土星
Mercury, Venus, Mars, Jupiter and Saturn.
并沒有遵守圓周運行軌跡的規律
Obstinately disobeying the law of the circle.
然而托勒密卻向我們證明
Nevertheless, Ptolemy shows us that
他們遵守圓周規律
they do obey.
他們之所以繞圈運動
The fact that we see them move in a loop
是由兩個天體環形運轉合力而為
is due to the joint effect of two circles.
其中一個繞地球旋轉
One that travels around the Earth
另一個沿著較小的圓形軌跡自轉
and another lesser circle prophet to each wanderer.
看  那是本輪
Look, the epicycles.
你們所看到的并非真正的規律
See, it's not heaven or earth.
只是雙眼蒙騙了我們
But our eyes that deceive us.
說的真好  達烏斯
Well said, Davus.
你的講解證明
I'd like you to know that your exposition shows me
你比在座的某些人更加用心
that you've been paying closer attention than One or two,others here.
聽著  上帝在造物之前
I tell you, the gods should have consulted me
都應該先征詢我的意見
before they created anything.
你這從何說起  俄瑞斯特斯
Why do you say that, Orestes?
所有的這些都太古怪了
It all seem so whimsical!
為什么是兩個天體  環形運轉合力而為呢
Why the joint effect of two circles?
如果行星不按自己的本輪公轉
Wouldn't it be more perfect, if the wanderers didn't wander,
而只按一個環形軌跡公轉  不是更合理嗎
and a single circle gave sense to everything?
俄瑞斯特斯  你有什么資格  評判上帝的杰作
Orestes, by what authority do you judge the work of God?
我哪兒得罪你了嗎?  基督徒
What is wrong with you, Christians?
難道人都不能開口說話了嗎?
Can a man no longer open his mouth in this city?
你批判天地萬物  你批判我們的主
If you criticize creation, you criticize our Lord and you offend us.
因而你冒犯了我們
You should move out to the desert.
你該搬到沙漠里去
You won't hear anything,
這樣你永遠都不會聽到這些逆耳之詞
to offend you out there.
你們不知所云  所有人都如此
You know nothing of what you speak. None of you.
辛奈西斯  歐基里得的第一公理是什么?
Synesius, what is Euclid's first rule?
你為什么問這個?
Why the question?
只要回答我
Just, answer me.
那個
If,
等于同量的量
if two things are equal to a third thing,
彼此相等
then they are all equal to each other.
很好
Good.
你們都和我非常熟識吧
Now, are you both not similar to me?
是的
Yes.
那你呢?  俄瑞斯特斯
And you, Orestes?
也是
Yes.
在此我向你們鄭重聲明
Now, I'm actually saying this to everybody here in this room.
我們要團結而不是分裂
More things unite us than divide us.
無論外面事態如何  我們都親如手足
Now, whatever maybe going on in the streets. We are brothers.
我們親如手足
We are brothers.
我希望你們記住
I want you to remember
我們并非奴隸或者烏合之眾
that brawls are for slaves and periphera.
現在我們用熱烈的掌聲
Now I think we should all honor Davus,
感謝達烏斯為我們講解這些知識
with some very well earned applause.
他們會決定我們每個人是生是死
He'll judge us all alive and dead.
到了那個時候就為時已晚
And then it will be too late,
只有那些信仰耶穌的人
because only those who believed in Jesus
才能得到救贖
will be saved.
你們此時不皈依吾主
What are you waiting for?
更待何時
上帝之國在你我上方
The Kingdom of God is upon us.
你們聽懂我說的話了嗎?
Do you understand what I'm telling you?
聽懂了
Yes.
你們明白要像個人嗎?
Yeah but do you understand like men do?
或者你們不明白  就像只小羊羔
Do you, not your head, a sheep?
你在這看什么?
What are you looking at?
對  就是你
Yes, you.
你在這里干什么?
What are you looking here?
你是阿摩尼阿斯嗎?
Are you Ammonius?
那個創造奇跡的人
The man who performed the miracle?
你想看到奇跡嗎?
Do you want to see a miracle?
你是他嗎?
Are you the one?
我是
I am.
跟我來
Come with me.
耶穌走遍加利利
Jesus went throughout Galilee
在各會堂里教訓人
teaching in their synagogues.
傳送天國的福音
Preaching the good news for you
醫治百姓各樣的病癥
and healing the diseases of sick.
他的名聲就傳遍了敘利亞
News about him spread going to Syria
來自世界各地的人們  都慕名前來朝拜他
and people came from all over the world.
那是西奧勒斯
That is Theophilus.
我們的主教
Bishop.
因為天國是他們的
For theirs is the Kingdom of Heaven.
哀慟之人有福了
Blessed are those who mourn
因為他們必得安慰
for they will be comforted.
溫柔之人有福了
Blessed are the meek
因為他們必繼承土地
for they will inherit the earth.
饑渴慕義之人有福了
Blessed are they which do hunger and thirst for righteousness
因為他們必得飽足
for they will be filled.
天主的世界
The word of God!
憐恤人之人有福了
Blessed are the merciful
因為他們必蒙憐恤
for they will be shown mercy.
清心之人有福了
Blessed are the pure in heart,
因為他們必得見神
for they will see God.
天主與你同在
The Lord be with you.
你是怎么穿過那火焰的?
So how are you able to escape the flames?
-天主與你同在  -也與你同在
-The Lord be with you. -And with you.
你覺得呢?我祈禱而已
What do you think I did? I prayed.
你可能都不知道該如何祈禱吧?
You probable do not even know how.
你那包里有什么?
What do you have in that sack?
-有吃的嗎?  -這是我主人的
-Do you have any food here? -It's for my Master.
你沒什么毛病吧?
What's wrong with you?
給你的話  我就得自己掏腰包了
I have to pay for that with my own money!
你要錢干什么?
What do you need money for?
看看他們的眼神
Look at their faces.
來
Here.
我想讓你自己來試試
I want you to try it yourself.
然后我教你怎么祈禱
And afterwards I will teach you how to pray.
來
Go on.
-天主與你同在  -主保佑你
-The Lord be with you. -Bless you.
看見了嗎?
See?
這就是奇跡
That is a miracle!
繼續  接著發
Go on, keep doing it.
神與你同在
The Lord be with you.
謝謝
Please.
謝謝你
Thank you.
神保佑你
Bless you,
主保佑你
God bless you.
保佑你
Bless you.
奴隸
Hey, slave!
你叫什么名字?
What is your name?
達烏斯
Davus.
奴隸達烏斯
Davus the slave!
你像個真正的基督圣戰士
Now, you look like a true parabolani.
一名真正的耶穌的戰士
A true soldier of Christ.
他們說什么呢?
What are they saying now?
讓他們跳舞
Telling them to dance.
他們正暢飲美酒呢
The men are now heavy with wine.
出海旅行
All aboard!
多么不幸的旅途
Oh what an unfortunate wreck.
救救你的奴仆吧
Save your servants!
第二幕結束
End of Part Two!
謝謝觀看  各位觀眾
Thank you, audience, thank you.
我們現在要更換道具以及演出服裝
Now, excuse the delay while we move things around,
希望大家諒解
and change our costumes.
不好意思
Good evening
原諒我的大膽
Forgive my boldness.
我是俄瑞斯特斯
I am Orestes,
俄瑞斯特斯家的兒子
son of Orestes.
我在這
I'm here to,
我在這想說出  對哲學家希帕蒂亞的愛意
I'm here to declare my love for Hypatia, the philosopher.
而她也深知這點
I mean, you all no doubt know
我采納了她給我的建議
for some time now, following her counseling.
我投身于音樂當中
I have devoted myself to music.
希望在聲音的和諧中尋求到一絲慰藉
In the hope of seeking solace in the harmony of its sounds.
但對我來說
But for me,
只有我傾慕的女士身上才有這種和諧
such harmony resides only in my lady.
所以
So,
我站在這只是為了
My purpose here is merely to,
獻上我的音樂
offer my melody
并且希望
in the hopes of,
不用再說了
Stop talking.
那人肯定很有前途
That man will go far, I tell you.
如果我準備的是香蕉而不是無花果
He's my preferred fruit for the banana not the fig,
我早就扔在他腳下了
I would have already fallen at his feet.
你準備怎么回禮呢?
Wouldn't it be best to please him?
我嗎?
Me?
怎么回禮?
How?
格來提  你能阻止的了你的女兒嗎?
Granting him your daughter's hand.
難道你不打算讓她嫁人嗎?
Why don't you ever plan to marry her off?
希帕蒂亞嫁給一個男人  不讀書不教書
Hypatia subject to a man? Without freedom to teach?
甚至不談她的那些想法嗎?
Or even to speak her mind.
我認識的最杰出的哲學家
The most brilliant philosopher I know
必須要放棄科學
having to give up her science.
不  那會讓她生不如死的
No, that could be death to her.
沒錯  她的工作受人敬仰
It's true. Her work is admirable.
并且她德才兼備
That she's brilliant and virtuous.
可是賽昂
But Theon,
別忘了她的處境啊
She has not found her gift.
她只是個女人
Being a woman, I mean.
我們在天上的父  宅心仁厚
Our Father who art in heaven,
別讓她答應別人
Don't let anyone have her.
求你別讓她答應別人
Please, don't anyone else have her.
別讓別人  別讓她答應任何人
Don't let anyone else have her.
阿門
Amen.
早安  老師
Good day, lady.
早安
早安  老師
Good day lady.
昨天很多人看到  你們的同學把他的樂器
Yesterday, many of you would have seen one of your colleagues
獻給了我
present me an ollos
我接受了禮物
I accepted the gift.
而今天我也想回送給他一份禮物
And today I wish to make him earn a gift of my own in return.
這是給你的
This is for you.
這是我的經血
It is the blood of my cycle.
俄瑞斯特斯你
Orestes you,
你說你在我身上找到了和諧
You say that you have found harmony in me.
那我建議你看看周圍
Well, I am suggesting that you look elsewhere
因為我覺得周圍也存在著
because I think that there is little harmony or,
和諧和美麗
beauty in that.
你覺得呢?
Don't you agree?
昨天我們談到了阿波羅尼斯錐
Yesterday we were discussing the Apollonian cone.
我們講了圓形  橢圓  拋物線
We discussed the circle, the ellipse, the parabola.
-今天我們來講雙曲線  -老師
-Today we will discuss the hyperbola. -Lady!
不好意思  老師
Forgive me, Lady.
奧林匹斯要你趕快到神廟去
Olympius requires your presence urgently in the Serapeum.
你們也是
You as well.
感謝主  感謝主
Thank you, Lord. Thank you, Lord.
感謝主
Thank you, Lord.
難道我們要忍受他們詆毀我們的信仰
How are we to enjoy them force feeding us the faith
習俗  甚至我們的人民嗎?
and customs to people who until recently becoming outlaws?
-發生什么事了?  -這是種褻瀆
-What's happening? -It's despicable. A sacrilege.
基督徒已經在城市廣場集會了
Christians have gathered in the Agora.
他們在嘲弄我們的神明
They are mocking the gods.
我們必須阻止這些褻瀆
We must put an end these insults!
他們也許不怕他
They may not fear him,
但他們一定會怕我們的利劍
but they will fear our swords.
等等
Wait!
你們要干什么?
Now, what is it you are going to do?
你們要去襲擊他們嗎?
Are you going to attack them?
只因為他們的無禮  就讓他們血濺當場嗎?
Are you going to stain your hands with blood for an insult?
是對神明們  對神明們的褻瀆
To the gods! An insult to the gods!
如果你覺得他們過分
Well, if you think it is so outrageous then go
應該直接去通知本地的提督
and announce their acts before the prefect.
你好像在保護他們
One might think that you're protecting them.
我在盡力保護我們的學生們
I am trying to protect our disciples.
而你  在煽動他們成為野蠻的殺人犯
You, are inciting them to be violent murderers.
賽昂  作為首領  由你來決定吧
Theon, as director, you have the last word.
必須壓制他們對神明們的不敬
The insult must be answered.
猶太教徒可以自愿參加
Those Jews amongst you do as you please.
這不是你們的戰爭
This is not your battle.
而這里的基督徒們
As for you Christians
你們最好去找你們的耶穌
you would do well to join those of your own fate.
你不能讓我的學生走出這個建筑
You will not caused my disciples out of this house!
-塞拉皮斯萬歲  -為了神明們
-Glory be to Serapis! -And all the gods!
等我的命令
Wait for my command!
在我們包圍他們前  不會有人懷疑我們的
No one must suspect us until we have them surrounded.
這些劍是給奴隸的  奴隸們
The clubs are for the slaves. Slaves!
奴隸也要參加
Slaves are all for summon!
達烏斯  回去
Davus, back.
不  回去
No. Go back.
殺了基督徒
Death to Christians!
塞拉皮斯萬歲
Glory be to Serapis!
讓我們聆聽她的聲音
Let's listen to her now!
你們聽到她的抱怨了嗎?
Do you hear any complaint?
沒有
No!
這一座也失聲了
This one has lost her voice too!
他們的嘴不能說話
Their mouths do not speak,
他們的眼看不到東西
their eyes do not see,
他們的鼻子聞不到味道
their nose doesn't smell.
但多神教徒卻要跪倒在他們面前
Yet still, pagans come here and kneel before them.
這是多么的瘋狂啊
What madness is this?
順從神明們的旨意
For the gods!
梅多羅
Medorus!
Take care of your master! Protect it,!
上帝只有一個
God is one!
打倒異教徒
Death to the pagans!
你  你看什么呢?  打啊
You! What are you looking at? Get there and fight!
打啊
Fight!
你聾了嗎?  我說打啊
Are you deaf? I said fight!
我是個基督徒
I'm a Christian!
I am a Christian!
我是個基督徒
-什么是基督?  -基督是神
-What is Christ? -Christ is one!
打倒異教徒
Death to the pagans!
上帝只有一個
God is one!
不  不
No! No!
入口  我們必須守住入口
The entrance! We must defend the entrance!
怎么了?
What's happening?
我們的人被基督徒打敗了
Our men are being sent back by the Christians!
父親
Father!
沒事  沒事
It's alright. It's alright.
怎么了?
What happened?
是他的奴隸干的
It was his slave.
達烏斯  給我拿些布那些水來  快
Davus, get me some cloth some water, quickly.
父親
Father,
辛奈西斯  我們得離開這里
Synesius, we must get out of here.
扶住他別動
Hold him still.
基督徒們來了
Parabolani are coming!
上帝與我們同在
God is with us!
哈利路亞  哈利路亞
Hallelujah! Hallelujah!
-關上大門  -別  我們的人還在外面
-Close the gates! -You know our men are still out there!
愿神明們保佑他們
May the gods protect them.
我說關上大門
Close the gates,I said!
別殺他  我們把他留作人質像那其它基督徒一樣
Don't kill him! He'll be our hostage like the others.
大家都聽見了嗎?
Did you hear it everyone?
你抓到的所有基督徒
Any Christian you catch
如今都是人質
is now a hostage.
把我們的傷者送去寺院
Take our wounded to the temple
基督徒帶到地下室去
and the Christians down into the cellars.
眼神好的人去暀W觀察情況
And anyone with a good eye and a good aim up on the walls.
奧林匹斯
Olympius.
他是個基督徒
This one is a Christian.
沒錯  還有那三個
Yes, and those three as well.
如果他們是基督徒  他們就得去地下室
If they are Christians, they will go down to the cellars.
奧林匹斯
Olympius
如果你要囚禁我的兄弟們
if you are going to imprison my brothers
你就得把我也關起來
then you are going to have to imprison me with them.
如果必須如此  我會這樣做的
If it is necessary, I will do that.
如果任何人
If anyone,
任何人
anyone,
敢碰我兄弟們一根指頭
dare lay a finger on one of my brothers
我發誓我會刺穿他的身體
I swear I'll run in for you.
看
Look!
看這個
Look at this!
俄瑞斯特斯
Orestes.
謝謝你
Thank you.
什么時候開始?
Since when were there
有這么多基督徒的
so many Christians?
我們不得不和他們談判了
We'll talk to them to negotiate.
我們在等什么?
What are we waiting for?
一個基督徒君主能做些什么呢
What can we expect from a Christian emperor?
除非我們收起刀劍
Except we'll be put in a sword.
至少我現在活了下來
Our sense of positive being the life when his verdict arrives.
小心
Here will do.
請大家都不要擅自行動
No one should leave the group, please.
他們要整夜祈禱嗎?
Are they going to pray all night?
達烏斯
Davus.
待在這兒
Stay here.
這里很安全
It's safer here.
好好的留在這吧
Just stay with him first.
辛奈西斯  你要干什么?
Synesius! What are you doing?
老師  姐姐  母親
Lady, sister and mother,
愿主祝福并保護你
May God bless you and protect you.
退后
Move back!
奴隸至死都吃這個
Slaves take it to the back.
奴隸排最后
Slaves get to the back!
三個一出現了
If this three one come out.
會是場災難
It's a disaster.
父親  你什么時候才能不擲骰子?
Father, why don't you leave the dice?
今天有人看過傷口了嗎?
Have you been seen today?
-沒有  -沒有嗎?
-No. -No?
讓我看一下
Let's have a look.
孩子  向我保證
Promise me, my child, that,
在我死后  忘記現在這個愚蠢的老頭
when I'm gone, you won't remember this foolish old man.
我保證
I promise.
記住我曾經的樣子
Remember me as I was before.
記住那個還能思考  并且
Before when I could still think and,
我
I,
與你共事的我
work with you and,
記住我傾聽你心事時的樣子
I listen to you.
我怎么會犯下這樣的大錯?
How could I have been so wrong?
如今因為我的錯誤  讓你被困在這里
Seeing you here locked up because of my,
父親  請別說了
Father, please.
我希望你能夠自由
I wanted you to be free.
我是自由的
I am free.
基督徒們
Hey, Christians.
Christians!
你們對上帝的那份自信哪兒去了?
What's that confident God of yours doing now?
進棺材吧  人渣
Maybe coffins for you, scums!
告訴我
So tell me.
那些神如今在哪里?
Where are the gods now?
他們在哪?
Where are they?
-可能也去找別人了吧?  -別人
-Might as well look for others. -Others?
哪一個?  基督徒的上帝嗎?
Which one? The God of the Christians perhaps?
真是太放肆了
Such boldness!
你怎么想  老師?  你是如此的勇敢
What do you think, Lady? You are so bold.
把這盆火滅掉
Put the fire out.
你的確很大膽
You are indeed bold.
非常大膽
Very bold.
我一直在想你對我說過的那些事
I've been thinking about something you said to me.
我嗎?
Me?
那天你質疑天體的運動軌跡
That day that you criticize the heavenly mechanism
而且你把它稱為無稽之談
and you called it whimsical.
是的  盡管
Yes, although,
其實
Actually,
我是在質疑托勒密的理論
I was criticizing Ptolemy.
他的本輪理論讓一切都變復雜了
For complicating everything with his epicycles.
但我不確定  也許只是有些欠考慮
I don't know perhaps I'm just simple-minded.
不是
No.
天空之上
No, the heavens
應當是簡單的
should be simple.
那么我是對了還是
So am I right or,?
如果
What if,
如果有個更簡單的理論可以解釋
What if there were simpler explanations
那些行星又當如何?
for the wanderers?
有的
There is.
但卻太荒謬了  太陳舊了
But it is so absurd, so old.
沒有人愿意相信它
That no one gives it any credit.
那是什么理論?
What theory is that?
你是在說阿里斯塔克斯嗎?
Do you think of Aristarchus?
阿里斯塔克斯認為
Aristarchus maintained
地球本身在移動
that the earth moves.
而幾大行星的奇怪行為
The strange behavior of the wanderers
僅僅是我們的星球
was nothing more than an optical illusion
在圍繞著太陽運動時
caused by our movement
所產生的光學幻覺而已
in combination with Earth around the sun.
-以太陽為中心的模型  -是的
-Heliocentric model. -That's right.
太陽在中心
The sun would be in the center
仿佛它是宇宙眾星的尊貴之王
acting as speaking of it as "King of the Stars".
-讓我們變成了  -他的著作
-It would make Earth just,another wanderer. -His work was lost
在主圖書館的一場大火中被燒毀了
in the fire that destroyed the mother library.
這就是我們必須好好保護  這地方的原因
This is why we have to take great care of this place.
我們的圖書館
Our library
存留著人類的所有智慧
is all that remains of the wisdom of men.
但每次扔一個物體
But everytime you drop an object here.
誰在說話
Who speaks?
原諒我  女主人
Forgive me, Mistress.
我一直在聽
I was listening.
說吧  達烏斯
Speak up, Davus.
如果地球在移動
If the earth is moving,
每當扔下一個物體
every time dropping an object it would,
它就會落到后面才對
fall further behind.
而風應該會保持迎面吹來
And the wind would always blow against us.
鳥兒會迷失航向
And the birds would lose their way in flight.
我跟你說過
I told you
阿里斯塔克斯的假說一點都講不通
Aristarchus' hypothesis makes no sense at all.
我覺得你剛才說的可以被駁倒
I feel that what you just said can be refuted.
但現在我不知道如何去駁倒
But right now I don't know how.
給提督讓道
Make way for the prefect!
讓開
Make way!
給提督讓道
Make way for the prefect!
讓開
Make way!
大家都聽著
Listen one and all!
請大家認真聽并遵守君主的裁決
Prepare to hear and obey the verdict of our Emperor.
我  弗拉維烏斯·狄奧多西·奧古斯都
I, Flavius Theodosius Augustus
獵戶區省的君主和最高行政長官
Emperor and Supreme Head of the provinces of the Orient,
最近了解到
having been informed of the events,
在亞歷山大城發生的大事
which recently took place in the City of Alexandria,
特此宣布并命令大家
do hereby declare and command
這些起義者將會得到保護
that the insurgents shall be pardoned and freed.
而作為我寬宏大量的交換
In exchange for my generosity,
起義者必須馬上
the insurgents will
離開神殿和圖書館
abandon the Serapeum and the Library immediately
同時允許基督徒進入
allowing the Christians to enter
并處理掉所有卷軸
and dispose off the premises
按其心意
as they see fit.
我們在期待什么?  他們會毀掉一切的
What are we to expect? They'll destroy everything!
多神教徒將會從后門離開
Pagans will leave by the stable.
那些書
The Books.
從那里你們會被護送至你們的家里
And they will be escorted to their homes.
馬上執行
Obey this, instant!
派一半軍隊去那邊
Send half of the regiment to the other side.
其余的等會過去
and send the rest later.
是的  長官
Yes, sir.
提督
Prefect.
我們這樣堅持不了多久
We won't be able to contain this, not for long.
以十字架的名義  以十字架的名義
On the cross! On the cross!
留下那些次要的書
Leave the lesser works.
-哪些是次要的?  -拿走那些重要的
-Which are the lesser works? -Just take the important ones. The important ones.
士兵們后撤了
The soldiers are withdrawing!
奴隸
Slave!
-你們看到我的女主人了嗎?  -快過來幫忙
-Have you seen my mistress? -Just get over here and help!
-我們拿不了這么多  -我們需要更多幫助
-They're not carrying so many. -We need more help.
請帶我的父親離開這里
Please go and get my father out of here.
快帶他離開這里
Get him out of here now.
奴隸
Slave!
快  快走  快走
Go! Go! Go! Go!
快點  快點
Come on, quickly!
希帕蒂亞和他的學生還在正廳里
Hypatia and her students are still in the atrium.
他們瘋了嗎?
Are they out of their minds?
既然他們想那樣  就隨他們去吧
If that's what they want, let them burn.
快點
Come on!
Quickly!
小姐
Lady.
你去哪兒了?  把那個袋子撿起來
Where have you been? Pick up that sack.
-小姐我們得走了  -把那個袋子撿起來
-Lady We have to go. -Pick up the sack!
為什么到需要的時候  奴隸總是不在身邊
Why are slaves never around when you needed them?
-我剛才在  -快點走啊  快點
-I was, -Move!, move your feet, move!
白癡
Idiot!
快跑
Run!
快點  沒有時間了
There is no time!
老師
Lady!
別管這些了
Leave them.
上帝只有一個
God is one!
趕快
Run!
達烏斯
Davus!
你要去哪兒?
Where are you going?
-我們得走了  -達烏斯  你要去哪兒?
-We have to go! -Davus, where are you going?
如果他想為我們的神而死  就隨他吧
If he wants to die for our gods, let him.
達烏斯  不要  不要這樣做
Please, no. Please don't do this.
-快點  -達烏斯
-Come on! -Davus!
-達烏斯  不要  -快走
-Davus, no! -Come on!
以十字架的名義
God is one!
哈利路亞  哈利路亞  哈利路亞
Hallelujah, hallelujah, hallelujah!
奴隸
Slave!
達烏斯
Davus!
奴隸達烏斯
Davus the slave!
幫我弄倒這個
Help me with this!
幫我
Help me!
哈利路亞  哈利路亞  哈利路亞
Hallelujah, hallelujah, hallelujah!
多神教徒的人渣
Pagan sinners!
最沉重的傷痛都過去了
The Master's wound is festering.
我知道
I know.
達烏斯
Davus.
Davus!
你自由了
You're free.
走
Go.
走吧
從現在開始  在亞歷山大
Hence forth, in Alexandria
只許舉行基督教和猶太教的慶典
only Christian and Jewish worship shall be permitted.
禁止一切多神教的祭祀
Pagan sacrifices,
禁止膜拜多神教的象征物
worshipping pagan symbols
禁止參觀多神教教堂
and visiting pagan temples shall no longer be allowed.
任何人敢這么做或注視它們的
Should anyone commit such an act or dare raise his eyes on the statues
古老神像  都將會得到嚴厲的懲罰
of former gods. He shall be punished without penance.
圖書館淪陷后  許多多神教徒皈依基督教
希帕蒂亞則繼續教學和進行研究
而他之前的學生
成為了社會的中流砥柱
整個帝國被一分為二
許多基督徒認為  這是世界終結的前兆
于是決定過更神圣的生活
基督教圣戰士穿梭在大街小巷
精力充沛地監督基督徒的品行
而猶太教徒的存在讓他們無法釋懷
該死的猶太人
Damn Jews!
他們只是一群沒用的惡棍  畜生
They're just a bunch of good for nothing thugs, packed animals!
喬瑞恩  我親愛的朋友  冷靜點
Joran, my dear friend, calm down.
讓西里爾主教解釋一下吧
Let Bishop Cyril speak in his own defense.
提督
Prefect
我們那些神圣的圣戰士
our blessed parabolani,
他們僅僅是
Whom he has just called
在打拍子而已
the Beast of Burden.
只是為了附和他們打拍子而已
Devote themselves true enough to carrying burdens.
他們都是殘疾人或者病人
crippled, the sick, the lepers,
還有石頭
And stones!
提督  他們帶了石頭
Prefect, they carry stones.
突然沖進劇院
And now, they burst into the theatre
他們知道我們無法自衛  還用石頭砸我們
and stone us knowing we will do nothing to defend ourselves.
因為今天是安息日
Because it is the Sabbath!
在安息日這天  你們應該
On the Sabbath you should honor God
在猶太教會堂向主祈禱
in your synagogues instead stuffing yourselves
而不是在劇院欣賞戲劇
with sweet set of theater.
正因為這個石頭才會落到你們頭上
That is why the stones fell upon you.
提督  聽到了嗎?  他威脅我們  這太過分了
Prefect, do you hear that? Now, he's threatening us. This is too much.
友愛些  我們是合眾院
Friends, there are more things that unite us than divide us.
我們是兄弟  我們全都親如手足
We are brothers! We're all brothers.
沒有猶太人哪會有你們基督徒?
Where would you Christians be without the Jews?
耶穌就是猶太人
Jesus was a Jew!
我發現了點東西
There is,something I find
可以反駁你所說的
disturbing in what you've told me.
-是什么?  -好吧
-What?  -Well,
西里爾為什么要開始清理城市?
Why does Cyril speak of cleaning up the city?
他已經擁有這么多了還不滿足嗎?
Is he not satisfied with what he already has?
他只想嚇嚇猶太人
I think he's just trying to frighten the Jews.
可為什么要當你的面說?
But why say it in front of you?
如果他想對付的是你  而不是他們怎么辦?
What if really he was addressing you and not them?
我  為什么?  我和他一樣都是基督徒
Me? Why? I'm as much as Christian as he is.
是的  可你忘記了
Yes, but you forget
你圈子里許多人不是基督徒
that many of us from your circle are not.
滿帆  提督
And a full sail, prefect.
走吧
Let's go.
-亞斯巴修  準備好了嗎?  -是的  女主人
-Aspasius, you ready? -Yes, mistress.
我要你拿著麻袋爬到桅桿的頂端
I would like you to take the sack and climb to the top of the mast.
好了  老師
And now, Lady,
你能給我解釋一下  這是怎么回事嗎?
Will you finally tell me what the point of all this is?
當亞斯巴修扔下麻袋的同時
When Aspasius drops the sack,
船在往前走
the boat will be moving forward.
因此麻袋
Therefore, the sack
不會掉在桅桿下
won't fall at the foot of the mast,
而是會掉得往后一些  我想大概
but will fall further back. I would say about,
大概會在這兒
about here.
這樣做有什么意義嗎?
And what is so special about that?
-太好了  -可你錯了
-Yes! -But you were wrong!
是  但這是決定性證據
Yes, but this is definite proof!
決定性的  麻袋就像是在靜止的船上那樣掉下來
It's definitive. The sack behaved as if the boat was stationary.
那意味著什么?
What does that mean?
我不知道
I don't know.
但同樣的原理也可以應用在地球上
But the same principle could be applied to the Earth.
它可能繞著太陽轉而我們卻不知道
It could be moving around the Sun without us realizing.
-阿里斯塔克斯的理論  -沒錯
-Aristarchus. -Exactly.
你為什么要那么執著呢  老師?
Why do you torment yourself with that, Lady?
托勒密理論雖不完善
Ptolemy's not perfect but,
但卻很管用
it works.
俄瑞斯特斯  當時是你提出的
Orestes, but you are the one who,
提督  幾年前你可沒有這么務實
A few years ago, you weren't so pragmatic, prefect.
幾年前我總是不經思考就發言
Well, a few years ago, I talked first and thought later.
我看到了仙王座三
I have Cepheus third.
三十七
37.
四十八
48.
金星和木星共同落在水瓶座里
Venus and Mars share house in Aquarius.
我父親定會用美酒慶祝這種結合
My father would have celebrated such a conjunction with a good wine.
-星星永遠不會落下  -真的嗎?
-The stars will not fall. -Oh really?
是的  因為它們都鑲在盒蓋上
No, because they're fixed to the lid of their chests.
蓋子會打開兩顆心  然后耶穌就誕生了
The lid will open in two hearts and then Jesus will appear.
你說的是什么盒子?
What chest are you talking about?
你不知道宇宙是個巨大的盒子嗎?
Don't you know that the universe is a gigantic chest?
天堂是蓋子  地球是底部
Heaven is the lid on top and the Earth, the ground,
他們沒告訴這個笨蛋地球是圓的
They haven't told this fool that the Earth is round.
地球是扁的
The Earth is flat.
你的腦袋是扁的
Your head is flat.
去看看圣經吧
Read the Scriptures!
如果地球是圓的
If the earth is round,
為什么住在下端的人們不會掉下去?
Why don't the people at the bottom fall off?
住在側面的人呢?
What about the ones on the sides?
他們為什么不會滑下去呢?
Why don't they slide off?
想想看
Think about that.
達烏斯知道
Davus knows.
兄弟
Hey, brother.
你有什么看法?
What do you say?
地球是扁的還是圓的
Is the earth is flat or round?
只有上帝才知道這些
Only God knows those things.
放在地上別動
Leave them on the ground!
別管它們  它們就該放地上
Leave them on the ground! That's where they belong.
女士  請您不要灰心喪氣
Lady, you must not lose heart.
今天在船上您已經取得了很大的進展
Today on the boat you made great progress.
為什么所有行星的亮度的變化
Why do the wanderers bury their brightness?
會如此變化無常
So unexpectedly.
更糟的是
And what is worse,
為什么太陽
Why does the sun?
為什么它的體積在夏天和冬天會不同
Why does it change size from summer to winter?
也許是因為它有時近
Perhaps because sometimes it is nearer,
有時遠
and other times it is farther away.
可是  亞斯巴修
But Aspasius
看
Watch.
按阿里斯塔克斯的理論  太陽一定
According Aristarchus, the sun must be
是在萬物的中心
at the center of everything.
而我們的地球
With us, the Earth,
繞著它沿圓周軌跡在公轉
traveling in a circle around it.
因此  這就是關鍵
Therefore, and this is the key.
我們和它一直
We're always at exactly,
保持著同樣的距離
the same distance.
如果按你說的  距離會改變
Now, if as you just said, we accept the changes in distance
那么我們就得
then we are forced to add
在地球軌道上加一個本輪
and epicycle to the Earth's orbit.
這樣它才會時近時遠
So it's going to be nearer and then it's going to be farther away.
這樣我們就陷入托勒密的謎團里了  .
But now we fall into the same trap as Ptolemy.
-圈套著圈  -沒錯
-Circle upon circles. -Exactly!
我不知道如何解決這個矛盾
So I just do not know how to resolve this conflict.
你覺得我們能解決
I mean, the only thing we could do is,
把太陽從中心移走  那么
displace the sun from the center and well,
并非必須在中心
not to have a center.
這讓我感到傷心  亞斯巴修
It breaks my heart, Aspasius.
告訴我  我該怎么做?
So tell me, what do I do?
休息一下吧  女士
Rest, lady.
基督圣戰士
Parabolani!
-圣戰士們  -怎么了?
-Parabolani! -What is happening?
圣戰士們  快來救命啊
Parabolani, quick! Help!
圣亞里罕德羅著火了
St. Alexander's on fire!
著火了
It is a fire.
快點
Come on!
去提水  拿上水桶  拿著這個
Gather water! Get the water! Quick! Take this!
快點
Hurry!
快
Quick!
快  快點  跑快點
Come on, come on!
圣戰士們
Parabolani!
圣戰士們啊
圣戰士  快啊
Parabolani, quick!
哪著火了?
Where's the fire?
在那邊  那邊
是猶太人  這是陷阱
Jews! It's a trap.
這是陷阱
It's a trap!
基督徒們
Christians, all.
昨夜是悲慘的一夜
Last night was a night to deplore.
現在我告訴你們
Now I say to you.
不要再為死去的兄弟們感到悲傷
Grieve no longer for our dead brothers.
不要哭泣
Weep not.
把眼淚留給其它人吧
Shed your tears for the others,
他們是劊子手
for they are executioners.
沒錯  沒錯
Yes, yes.
為那些干這件事的人哭泣吧
Weep for them. For those who have done this,
他們對上帝一無所知
Know not of God,
沒有愛  沒有同情心
nor of love nor of parity.
他們什么都不懂
They know not
因為今天他們重現了圣經里的情景
because it is they who repeat the words of the Scriptures
卻對此一無所知
with no understanding at all.
他們只看到一個人
It is they who saw only a man
那就是上帝的兒子  站在他們面前
when the Son of God was standing in front of them.
也正是他們愚昧地嘲笑他
And it is they who in their blindness
還將他釘死在十字架上
mocked him and crucified him.
哭泣吧  哭泣吧  為猶太人哭泣
Yes Weep! Weep for the Jews,
他們害死了我們的主
those evil butchers of our Lord.
因為上帝
Because God,
上帝已經責罰他們了
because God, God, God has already condemned them.
這是上帝的旨意
It is God's will,
讓他們成為奴隸
that they live as slaves
被詛咒  被流放  直到世界末日
cursed and exiled until the end of time.
被詛咒  被流放
Cursed and exiled!
女士  別停下  女士
Lady, do not stop, Lady.
所有的猶太人都想要復仇
Now all the Jews will want to retaliate.
恐怕你不清楚目前的狀況
I'm afraid you don't understand what's really happening.
一切結束后  亞歷山大  就不再有猶太人了
When this is all over, there will be no more Jews in Alexandria.
很抱歉這樣冒失地闖了進來
I'm sorry for busting in like this.
老師  你不該冒險來這里的
Lady, you should the risk of coming here.
軍隊在哪?
Where are the troops?
為什么街道上沒有士兵?
Why are there no more soldiers on the streets?
在那種混亂中  沒有軍隊  可以控制整個城市
No army could contain that mob. The entire city is in a frenzy.
他要求殺光所有的婦女和兒童
Calling to the annihilation of women and children.
他是主教
A bishop!
-他是基督徒  -那就把他關起來
-A Christian! Then lock him up.
提督  你應該逮捕他
Prefect. You should have him arrested.
事情沒那么簡單
It's not so easy.
女士  西里爾知道我們有相同的信仰
Lady, Cyril knows they both share the same faith.
這讓我們的長官進退兩難
That places our prefect in a very awkward position.
如果他為猶太人辯護
If he defends the Jews, half the city will rise up
會有一半的市民反對政府
against his government.
我明白了
I see.
可如果現在你什么都不做
But if you choose to do nothing now,
我相信西里爾  會繼續重復相同的事
I believe Cyril will continue to do the same thing over and over again and until,
直到殺光城里的最后一個人
until there is no one left in this city.
就沒人可以讓政府管理了
No people for this government to govern.
我太幼稚了
How naive of me.
我真幼稚  居然寄希望于最終的改變
How naive of me to think we have finally chose.
猶太人滾出去
Jews out!
他們先殺了他們
First, they kill them
然后埋了他們
then they bury them.
是昔蘭尼的主教
The Bishop of Cyrene.
-他來這兒干什么?  -我去看看
-What is he doing here?  -I'll find out.
這是我的小亞歷山大圖書館
It's my little library of Alexandria.
我在這里教孩子們知識
This is where I teach  the children.
阿波羅尼斯圓錐體
An Apollonian cone.
是的  我用它來教孩子們四種不同曲線
Yes, I built it to teach them about the four curves.
圓形
The Circle.
橢圓形
The ellipse.
俄瑞斯特斯應該早到了才對
Orestes should really be here by now.
拋物線
Parabola.
雙曲線
And hyperbola.
真是美極了
It's truly beautiful.
我常看著它去思考
You know, I often look at it and I always wonder
為什么相同的圓軸?
why does the circle coexist with such
會產生如此多不同的形狀
impure shapes?
不如我坐在這里再聽你講一次課
When I get to sit here and listen to you again.
看來讓你無聊了
I bore you.
我已經很久沒有教書了
It's been a long time since I've done anything but,
只是在研究天體系統上絞盡腦汁
beat my head against a stone.
然而卻無人關注它的重要性
Anyhow, there are more important matters at hand.
我來晚了
Forgive me.
一個多神教徒控制著兩個基督徒
Two Christians in the hands of a heathen.
真是不可容忍
It's an outrage!
-這里有多少?  -不知道  但會發出惡臭
-How many left? I don't know but it smells.
阿摩尼阿斯
Ammonius.
上帝跟你說過話嗎?
Does God speak with you?
你總是這樣
All the time.
阿摩尼阿斯這樣  阿摩尼阿斯那樣
Ammonius this, Ammonius that. Ammonius, Ammonius, Ammonius.
今天他對我說得極快
Today, he spoke to me
非常快  我不得不請求他說慢點
so quickly, I had to ask him slow down.
告訴我
Tell me something.
你認為我們是錯的嗎?
Do you ever think we're mistaken?
為什么這么說?
Why?
我曾被寬恕過
I always forgive and,
但現在  我無法寬恕別人
but now, I can't forgive.
寬恕
Forgive?
誰?
Who?
猶太人嗎?
The Jews?
耶穌在十字架上寬恕了他們
Well, Jesus pardon them on the cross.
耶穌是上帝
Jesus was God
只有他才有這種寬容心
and only He can show such clemency.
你怎么敢拿自己跟上帝相提并論
How dare you compare yourself to God?
兄弟
Brother.
我們現在還活著
We are still alive.
因為什么?
Why?
因為
Because it was
是上帝的旨意  讓我們沒被石頭打死
His will to save us from the stones.
上帝讓我們在此  行該做之事
God wants us here, doing what we do.
你不再相信這些了嗎?
Don't you believe in that anymore?
閣下
My Lord,
西里爾是個驕傲的男人
Cyril is a very proud man.
他同意會面  但只協商和平議題
He'll agree to meet, but he wouldn't discuss the Jews,
不商討猶太人問題
only discuss peace.
和平
Peace?
作為您卑微的參謀  我的建議是
My suggestion, as your humble adviser in this affair,
請您接受提議
is for you to accept.
和平是最重要的
Let peace be foremost.
-老師  你怎么看?  -我
-Lady, what do you think? -Well,I,
我覺得這個提議并沒有那么好
I don't think it's very encouraging.
為什么他來見俄瑞斯特斯?
Why would he want to come and see Orestes without any concrete proposals?
而且還有別的東西
And there's something else.
他要來見你
He won't come to you.
但需要你在圖書館和他見面
Demands he meet you in the Library,
在星期天的禮拜中
during the Sunday service.
在圖書館嗎?  為什么?
In the Library? Why?
那次搶占之后
Only Christians are being permitted to enter the Library
只有基督徒才能進入圖書館
since it was stoned.
這是挑釁
It is a provocation!
請允許我說幾句
Allow me to suggest.
如果你覺得你的到場
If you consider your presence
是如此的重要
so essential
為什么你不接受洗禮呢?
why not let yourself be baptized?
我們中的大多數人
The majority of us here,
包括最高長官  都已經接納了基督教
beginning with our prefect, have accepted Christ.
剩余的這些人為什么不行呢?
Why not the rest of you?
這只是個時間問題  你們心知肚明
It's only a matter of time and you know it!
是嗎?
Really?
這真的只是個時間問題嗎?
It is just a matter of time?
請容許我說幾句
Well, excuse me,
尊敬的元老  但據我所知
honored member but as far as I'm aware
你們的上帝并不能證明他自己
your God has not yet proved himself
比他的前任們更公正更仁慈
to be more just or more merciful than his predecessors.
老師
Lady.
讓我接受你們的信仰  真的只是時間問題嗎?
Is it really just a question of time before I accept your faith?
那是什么?
Why, then,
難道這次會議
should this assembly
要接受一個毫無信仰的人
accept the counsel of someone who admittedly
提出的提議嗎?
believes in absolutely nothing?
我信仰哲學
I believe in philosophy.
哲學
Philosophy.
正是現在這種時候
Just what we need
我們所需要的東西
in times like this.
夠了
Enough!
這些年來  我一直在研究
All these years, I've been studying.
完全沒有了自己的生活
With absolutely no life of my own.
我想知道  我這樣為了什么?
And I wonder, what was the point?
忘了今天那些話吧
Whoa, forget about what was said today.
是生活困住了我嗎?
Is this all life holds for me?
還能是什么?
What else?
我覺得沒人能看出
I doubt anyone could see as a,
你是一位忠誠的妻子
devoted wife
一位盡心的母親
and mother.
我認為
I think,
城里的所有人都聽說了手帕的故事
I think everyone in the city knows the story of the handkerchief.
所以
So,
我父親也會喜歡女人
My father loved a woman.
連他也不例外
Even he,
有誰不愛呢?
Who have I ever loved?
除了你
Except you,
黎巴農斯
Libanius.
如果我能
If I could just,
解開這個謎團
just unravel this,
只需要再多努力一點
just a little bit more.
只要離答案再接近一些  那么
And just get a little close to the answer then,
這樣  我就能
then I would,
我就能安然入土
then I would go to my grave a happy woman.
為什么?
Why?
為什么這些對你如此重要?
Why does that mean so much to you?
就是現在
Right now,
就在這一秒  整個世界可能都在移動
this very second, the whole Earth could be moving
卻沒有人意識到這些
and no one realizes it.
只有你和我知道
Except you and me.
相信我  老師  幸虧沒人意識得到
Believe me Lady, it's best no one does.
你覺得這些真的不重要嗎?
Do you really not think it important?
我不明白你為什么
I don't understand
堅信人們腳下的土地是移動的呢
why you insist on moving the ground we walk on.
你也看到了船上發生的
Well, you saw for yourself what happened on the boat.
是的  但那也不能證明地球在移動
Yes, I did. But that does not necessarily mean the Earth moves.
如果確實是這樣呢?
What if it does?
希帕蒂亞  看看你的周圍
Hypatia, look around you.
死亡
Death,
恐懼
horror
毀滅
destruction.
如果地球真的在圓形軌道中移動
If the stars move in a circle
他們為什么  不把完美分給我們一些呢?
why would they share their perfection with us?
所以我們沒有移動
So we do not move,
只是不在圓形軌道中
In a circle.
我們不是按照圓形
We don't move,
運動的
Circle.
我們并非在圓形軌道中移動
We do not move in a circle.
從柏拉圖開始
Ever since Plato,
所有人  包括阿里斯塔克斯  希巴克斯  托勒密
all of them: Aristarchus Hipparchus, Ptolemy,
所有人都試圖用圓形軌道
they have all tried to reconcile their observations
來解釋他們的觀察結果
with circular orbits but,
但如果在宇宙中隱藏著其它形狀呢?
What if another shape is hiding in the heavens?
其它形狀
Another shape?
女士  沒有任何形狀比圓形更完美
Lady, there is no shape purer than the circle.
這是你教我們的
You taught us that.
我知道  只是假設
I know, but suppose just suppose the,
正是圓形的完美
purity of the circle
讓我們忽視了其它的一切
has blinded us from seeing anything beyond it.
就像耀眼的太陽讓我們
The same way that the glare of the sun
看不見星星一樣
blind us from actually seeing the stars.
我必須重新
I must begin all over with,
重新審視這個問題
with new eyes.
我必須重新思考一切
I must rethink everything.
所有的一切
I have to rethink everything.
從保羅寫給提摩太的第一封信開始讀
Reading from the first letter of Paul to Timothy.
我渴望男人  無處不在
I desire therefore, that everywhere
舉起圣潔的手  隨處禱告
men should lift up holy hands in prayer
無忿怒  無爭論
without anger or disputing.
同樣  又愿女人
In like manner, I desire women
廉恥  自守
to dress modestly,
以正派衣裳為妝飾
with decency and propriety
不以編發
not with braided hair
黃金  珍珠
or gold or pearls
和貴價的衣裳為妝飾
or expensive clothes,
-只要有善行  -為什么讀這段?
-but with good deeds. -Why is he reading this passage?
不知道  首領
I don't know, prefect.
但我肯定這不是事先說好的那段
I assure you it is not the one we agreed on.
女人要沉靜學道
That a woman learn
一味的順服  我不許女人講道
in quietness and in full submission. I do not permit a woman,
也不許他轄管男人
to teach or to have authority over a man,
只要
but to be
沉靜
in silence.
這是上帝之言
This is the word of God!
阿門
Amen.
當耶穌把自己的神圣遺產
Jesus himself
托付給他的十二門徒時
knew this when he
他自己非常了解這些
entrusted his holy legacy to twelve men
全是男人
Men.
沒有一個女人
Not a woman among them.
但是
And yet,
我知道亞歷山大有些人
I know of some in Alexandria
他們仰慕某個女人并且對她的話
who admire and even trust
言聽計從
in the word of a woman.
哲學家希帕蒂亞
The philosopher Hypatia.
這個女人曾公然表示過
A woman who declared,
她對上帝的不忠
in public, her ungodliness.
她是個女巫
A witch!
官員們
Dignitaries,
你們現在應該全部信奉基督
it is time for you all to reconcile yourselves with Christ.
這是上帝之言
This is the word of God.
在圣經面前下跪  并接受真理吧
Kneel before it and embrace its truth.
跪下
Kneel.
他不準備跪下嗎?
Is he not going to kneel?
跪下
Kneel!
罪人
Sinner!
我是基督徒
I am a Christian!
-我是基督徒  -不  你不是
-I am a Christian! -You're not a Christian!
我是和你們一樣的基督徒
I'm as Christian as you are.
給提督讓路
Make way for the prefect!
讓路
Make way!
我是受過洗禮的基督徒
I am a baptized Christian!
我要殺了你
I'll kill you.
我是和你們一樣的基督徒
I am as Christian as you.
I am as Christian as you are.
怎么會發生這種事
I mean, how could such a thing be possible?
罪犯已經被繩之以法了
The culprit has been executed.
立即帶我去見提督
I would like you to take me to the prefect immediately.
女士  他親自下令
Lady, he himself gave the order
讓你待在家里等進一步的通知
for you to be confined to the house until further notice.
現在這種情況  我建議你  不要在街上出現
At the moment your presence on the streets is not advisable.
為什么?
For what reason?
西里爾對你進行了嚴厲的譴責
Cyril has made some serious accusations against you.
那么
And um,
他控訴我什么罪名?
What does he accused me of?
對上帝不虔誠
Ungodliness,
還有使用巫術
And witchcraft.
我知道了
I see.
你在為什么事而煩惱嗎?女士
Is something bothering you, Lady?
沒有
No.
不如你來告訴我你在擔心什么?
Why don't you tell me what's worrying you?
提督  咬住這個
Prefect, why don't you bite on it?
說
Speak.
昔蘭尼的主教想見您
The Bishop of Cyrene wishes to see you.
所有人都出去
All of you,
提督  傷口還沒處理好
Prefect, the wound is not yet closed.
出去  出去
Get out. Get out!
所有人出去
All of you out! Out!
你們沒能殺死我啊
Well, that went well.
你認為我也參與這件事了嗎?
You think I had a part on this?
如果我想背叛你  怎么還會來到你面前
Would I show my face here if I wanted to betray you?
-你是瞎了嗎?  -是的  我是瞎了
-Are you blind?  -I was, yes, I was blind.
他一直想要的
Well, it's my head.
是我的頭  他想讓我死
He's wanted all along, it's me,
隨后就有了這次襲擊
that snake is after.
這個政府
This government!
這座城市
This city!
聽著
Now, listen.
-戰爭即將到來  -我知道
-War is brewing. I know.
我知道
I know.
那么宣誓對我效忠吧
Do you swear your loyalty to me?
向國家宣誓  快
To the Empire? Do it.
要么譴責他  要么滾出去
Condemn him or get out.
我會這么做的
I will do it.
如果有必要  我甚至會跪下來
On my knees, if necessary.
而且不只如此
And not only that.
幾天之內  我可以召集其它省的主教
In a few days, I can gather other bishops from the province
和沙漠里的修道士們來對抗西里爾
and amongst from the desert all against Cyril.
但首先我要問你個問題
First, I must ask you a question.
俄瑞斯特斯  你相信耶穌嗎?
Orestes, do you believe in Jesus?
你問我什么?
Do I what?
-你相信耶穌嗎?  -你問我什么?
-Do you believe in Jesus?  -Do I what!?
你到底是真正的基督徒
Are you a true Christian?
還是你像那些寥寥眾生  僅僅臣服于
Or did you like so many others, only convert
-自己的政治生涯  -辛奈西斯
-to prosper in politics? -Synesius.
你為什么不下跪?
Why didn't you kneel?
-我有什么選擇?  -你為什么不下跪?
-What choice did I have? -Why didn't you kneel?
我還有什么選擇?
What choice did I have?
背叛希帕蒂亞
Betray Hypatia?
譴責她嗎?
Condemn her?
你會那么做嗎?
Would you have done that?
我絕不會冒犯上帝的
I would never offend God.
是他  是他冒犯了上帝
It's he, he is offending God. He is offending him.
他在歪曲圣經
He's twisting his words
他在曲解圣經的意思
he's using the Scriptures.
他只是在宣讀圣經
He read what is written.
有多少女人可以對你發號施令
How many women do you obey?
多少個?
How many?
你仰慕的同時  又能聽你傾訴  的女人有幾個
How many do you admire and listen to?
只有
Only
一個
One.
只有一個
Only one.
圣經
The Scripture,
圣經是正確的
The Scripture is correct,
只是由于在他的手中
and it was in His hands.
兄弟  你還不明白嗎?
Brother, don't you see?
你不明白你那樣做是在眾人面前
Don't you see the insult to God?
侮辱上帝嗎?
In front of everyone.
我不知道
I don't know,
我不知道該相信什么?
I don't know what, what I believe.
你必須告訴他
You have to tell him.
別跟我說  俄瑞斯特斯
Go tell him now, Orestes.
告訴上帝你相信圣經
Tell him you believe in what is written.
-我信奉  -別跟我說  去跟他說
-I believe, -Don't tell me. Tell Him.
告訴上帝
Tell God.
跪下
Kneel!
許多人至今都記得
Many are those who remember today the miracles
我們摯愛的兄長曾創造的奇跡
our beloved brother performed in life.
比如那次他將自己托付給圣父
Like the time he commended himself to the Father
踏過火堆卻毫發無損
and threw himself into fire and was not even singe.
阿摩尼阿斯
Ammonius,
因為英勇捍衛對基督的信仰而獻身
dead of bravely defending your faith in Christ.
我追封你為
I proclaim you a martyr.
圣徒
A saint.
從此以后你將會被人們稱為
From now on, you shall be known as,
圣圖梅西斯
Saint Taumasius.
我們要討回公道
We want justice!
公道
Justice!
愿上帝指引我們  我親愛的
May God show us the way,
圣戰士們  我言盡于此
my dear parabolani. Little else can I say to you.
尼帝亞的修道士有多少
What about the monks of Nitria?
他們至少有500人  而且
We can win at least 500 of them.
我們還有500人
plus 500 of our own men,
你以為這就夠了嗎?  他可是地區提督
Do you think that's enough? He's the prefect,
都有的軍隊都會保衛他
He has a whole army to protect him.
聽著
Listen!
我們何不找個簡單又有效的方法
Why don't we do something much more simple and effective?
你指的是什么?
What are you talking about?
我們可以傷害他最關心的東西
We can hurt him where it hurts most,,,
如何?
How?
-那個婊子  -誰啊?
-That whore. -Who?
如果我們敢于面對世界的本相會怎樣?
What if we dared to look at the world just as it is?
我們先摒棄那些先入為主的想法
Let us share for a moment every preconceived idea.
它會是什么形狀?  什么形狀?
What shape would it show us? What shape?
你曾說過問題在于太陽體積的不一致
You once said that the problem lies in the inconsistency of the sun.
沒錯  我說過  很好  說清楚一點
Yes I did, good,good Put it into words.
太陽一定要在中心  因為我們繞著它旋轉
The sun must be at the center, since we revolve around it.
與此同時
And at the same time,
它又在其它位置  因為它離我們時遠時近
in another position since our distance from it varies.
-沒錯  正是如此  -怎么會?
-Yes, exactly. -How?
它是如何同時占據兩個位置的?
How could it occupy two positions?
怎么同時占據兩個位置的?
How could I occupy two positions at once?
亞斯巴修
Aspasius,
沒錯  沒錯  就是那兒  另一個放在這兒
Yes, yes. There. And then the other one here.
保持相同的比例
Keeping the same proportion.
很好  把那端栓在火炬上
Good. Very good. Now, tie this end to that torch.
亞斯巴修
Aspasius.
我要你把這個想象成是地球
I want you to imagine that this is the Earth.
每把火炬代表
And that each of these flames represent
它距離太陽的兩個極限位置
the two extreme positions of the sun in relation to it.
也就是冬天和夏天
In winter and in summer.
如果這兩個位置都是同一個圓
What would happen if both these positions with the two centers
的圓心會是什么樣
of one and the same circle?
這是不可能的  主人
But it is impossible, mistress.
等等  圓是什么?
Wait. What do we know about a circle?
我們知道圓心
We know that the center of a circle
到圓周上任一點的距離總是相等
is always the same distance from any point along its perimeter.
-沒錯  -是的
-Exactly. Yes, so,
那如果我們把這個圓心分成兩個呢
What if I divide the center into two,
讓圓周上的點到
but what I keep constant
這兩個圓心的距離之和保持不變
is the sum of their two distances to the perimeter.
好吧  我給你演示一下  看著  當我沿著
Alright, look. I'll show you. Watch.  As I move this rod along
這個圓周移動棒子  繩子的一部分增加時
the cord, as one segment increases
另一部分就會減少  反之亦然
the other segment decreases, and vice versa.
因此兩者之和
Therefore the sum of the two is always going to be constant.
保持不變  你明白了嗎?
Do you see that?
如果我們把這個理論運用到
Now, what if we apply this
地球的移動之上呢?
to the movement of the Earth?
我們會
What,
得到
figure,
什么圖形呢?
will be obtained?
一個橢圓軌道
An ellipse!
太陽在它的一個焦點之上
With the sun at one of its foci.
因為
Because,
這種橢圓軌道
what is a circle except
除了它的焦點太近以至于
a very special ellipse
看上去似乎合二為一了  還能是什么別的
whose foci have joined so close together that they appear to be one.
或許只是異想天開而已  亞斯巴修
Perhaps, I'm completely raving, Aspasius.
為什么非這樣不可  也許我只是
I mean, why should this be so? Maybe I'm just,
也許我
Maybe I'm,
你怎么看?
What do you think?
很可能就是這樣的  主人
It could well be solved, mistress.
太好了  我們明天再繼續
Well done, we'll continue with this tomorrow.
去休息吧
Get some sleep.
-晚安  主人  -晚安
-Good night, mistress. -Good night.
謝謝你
Thank you.
達烏斯
Davus!
你在干什么?
What are you doing?
老師
Lady.
讓我看看
Let me see.
你去那邊坐下吧
Why don't you sit down?
大家都去哪了
Where is everybody?
請坐
Please sit down.
我有
I have,
我也有消息要告訴你
I have news for you too.
所有的已經皈依
All dignitaries
基督教的官員們
who have yet to embrace the Christian faith
將要在公眾面前
are to be baptized
接受洗禮
in public.
目的非常明確
The aim very clear:
為了增加擁護者  使市里所有的基督徒
It's to add to our cause, all the Christians in the city
以及正派人士們
decent folk, better
都為我盡忠
to fight for me.
你指的是宣揚信仰嗎?
You speak of battling faith.
非常好
Very well.
既然所有的事都已成定局
It seems everything seems to have been decided already.
我不懂你還讓我來這里做什么?
I don't understand why you required my presence here.
我又不是政府的一員
I am not a member of government.
你不是  但你更重要  你是我最信任的人
No, you are more than that. You are the person I trust most
眾人皆知
and everyone knows it.
你在說什么?
What can I say?
老師
Lady.
很多年前
Many years ago,
很多年前你教導我們
years ago, you taught us something.
如果
If,
等同于同量的量
If two are equal to a third they are,
彼此相等  還記得嗎?
all are equal to each other. Do you remember?
是的
Yes
我們三個  我們都是好人
The three of us, we are all good people.
你和我們一樣  都是虔誠的基督徒
And you, you are as Christian as we are!
辛奈西斯  你對你的信仰深信不疑
Synesius, you don't question what you believe.
但我不能
You cannot.
我必須懷疑
I must.
那真是太遺憾了
That's a pity,
老師
Lady.
莫大的遺憾
A great pity.
我們所尊敬的老師
Our revered teacher
竟然背棄了自己曾教給過我們的東西
taken away from what she herself taught us.
你以為我不知道你  所執迷那些愚蠢的事
Or do you think I'm not aware of the insane things you invoke.
-辛奈西斯  -地球圍繞太陽旋轉
-Synesius! With Earth moving around the Sun.
接下來又會是什么?  老師
What next, Lady, what next?
求你讓我離開吧
You must let me go.
讓我進去  讓我進去
Let me in! Let me in!
-我有話對她說  -一個圣戰士
-I'll go straight to her. -Why does she wanna see a parabolani?
-老師  -在我們逮捕你之前快滾
-Lady! Go away before we arrest you.
-走開  -亞斯巴修
-Leave! -Aspasius!
是我  達烏斯  達烏斯  放開我
It's me, Davus. Get off me.
-告訴他們你認識我  -你認識他嗎?
-Tell them who I am -I know this man, please.
是的  你想干嘛?
What do you want?
我有話對她說  她在哪?
I need to speak to the mistress. Where is she?
-女主人不在家  -十萬火急  她在哪?
-Mistress is not here. -It's urgent! Where is she?
她在提督宮殿里
She's at the prefect's palace.
-哪里?  -她在提督宮殿里
-Where? -The prefect palace!
-提督宮殿  -謝謝  快點滾
-Prefect's palace. -Thank you. Get out of here.
那到底是誰?
Who was that?
他以前是這兒的奴隸
He was a slave once.
等等  求你  等一下  求你了
Wait, please! Wait! I beg you.
如果你不同意的話  我就不能再保護你了
If you don't agree, I won't be able to protect you any longer.
我也不能和你交往
I won't be able to have dealings with you
甚至不能和你打招呼
neither greet you.
希帕蒂亞
Hypatia.
你還不明白嗎?
Don't you see?
沒有你我活不下去的
I can't go on without you.
我不行
I cannot.
沒有你我無法打敗西里爾
Without you, I can't defeat Cyril.
俄瑞斯特斯
Orestes.
西里爾已經贏了
Cyril has already won.
謝謝
Thank you.
但我不需要你們的保護
I do not need you.
達烏斯!
Davus!
兄弟  你要去哪里?
Brother! Where are you going?
我們找到她了
We found her!
婊子  快走
Come on, walk!
快走  罪人
Move it, sinner!
婊子
Whore!
妖女
Witch!
多神教的人渣
Pagan sinner!
走啊  快走
Move! Come on!
妖女
Witch!
把她扒光
Strip her naked!
站起來
Get up.
就這樣  這樣上帝  可以看清你的污穢  妖女
That's it. So that God can behold in all your filth, whore.
看清你如何蠱惑提督  娼婦
The way you knock the prefect so hard.
異教徒
Heathen!
娼婦
Whore.
看啊
Look,
她一點反應都沒有
she's not reacting.
把刀子插進她的皮膚她就叫得出來了
She will scream all right when we skin her alive.
-有多少人有刀子  -沒有
-How many of you have knives? -None.
不要讓不潔的血液玷污你們的雙手
Don't stain your hands with impure blood.
用石塊砸死她吧
Let's stone her!
-我們用石塊砸死這個妖女  -去找些石塊
-Let's stone this witch! -Get some stones.
-快點  我們扔俄瑞斯特斯的石頭
-Quickly! The ones we throw at Orestes.
還在這里
they are still here.
我看著她
I'll stay with her.
她暈過去了
She fainted.
希帕蒂亞的尸體殘缺不全  留下的部分
The body of Hypatia was mutilated and the remains,
被拖去游街  焚燒
were dragged through the streets and burned in a fire.
俄瑞斯特斯被永久性的放逐  而西里爾,
Orestes was outlawed forever and Cyril,
則掌握了亞歷山大的大權
took control of the power in Alexandria.
不久之后  西里爾被封為圣徒  教會圣士
Later, Cyril was declared a Saint and Doctor of the Church.
盡管希帕蒂婭的成果  沒有被保存下來
Although not any of Hypatia works remains,
但她仍然被后人當作杰出的天文學家
it is known that she was an exceptional astronomer,
并且以對圓錐曲線的研究而著稱
well-known for the mathematical study of conical curves.
1200年后
One thousand two hundred years later,
17世紀  天文學家約翰內斯·開普勒
in the 17th century, astronomer Johannes Kepler,
解釋了圓錐曲線之中的
described that one of those curves,,
橢圓  正是它主宰著星球的運動軌跡
the ellipse, governs the movement of the planets.